Guide to the Boris I. Bittker Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Boris I. Bittker papers
1938-2006
1959-1986
MS 1869
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
11
(22 Boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, legal pleadings, memoranda, newspaper clippings, reports, subject files, and writings that document Boris I. Bittker's career as a professor at Yale Law School from 1946 to 2006. In addition to voluminous materials relating to taxation, the papers also include correspondence and subject files relating to Bittker's book, Case for Black Reparations (1973), and a small amount of materials relating to his role in the prosecution of the case of Ex Parte Quirin as a lawyer in the Office of Lend-Lease Administration from 1942-1943. Accession 2014-A-060 contains course notes from Yale Law School, 1938-1941.
Bittker, Boris I., 1916-2005
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Daniel Bittker and Susan Bittker, 2006. Transferred from the Yale Law Library, 2013-2014.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Boris Irving Bittker was born on November 16, 1916, in Rochester, New York. He received his B.A. from Cornell University in 1938. Bittker attended Yale Law School and obtained his LL.B. in 1941. He clerked for Judge Jerome N. Frank on the U. S. Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit.
Bittker worked as an attorney in the Office of Emergency Management, Foreigh Economic Administration (Lend-Lease Administration) from 1942 until he was inducted into the Army. He served as an infantryman in Europe and was awarded a Purple Heart. In 1946, he returned to Yale Law School as an assistant professor and was thereafter promoted to the posts of Southmayd Professor (1951), Sterling Professor of Law (1970), and Professor Emeritus (1983). Bittker was a prolific author and renowed expert in taxation, as evidenced by his two most influential casebooks Federal Income, Estate, and Gift Taxation and Federal Income Taxation of Corporations and Shareholders.
Boris I. Bitter died on September 8, 2005, and was survived by his two children, Daniel Bittker and Susan Bittker.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, legal pleadings, memoranda, newspaper clippings, reports, subject files, and writings that document Boris I. Bittker's career as a professor at Yale Law School from 1946 to 2006. In addition to voluminous materials relating to taxation, the papers also include correspondence and subject files relating to Bittker's book, Case for Black Reparations (1973) and a small amount of materials relating to his role in the the prosecution of the case of Ex Parte Quirin as a lawyer in the Office of Lend-Lease Administration from 1942-1943. Accession 2014-A-060 contains course notes from Yale Law School, 1938-1941.
The Boris I. Bittker Papers were processed as a collaborative effort between Manuscripts and Archives and the Yale Law School to document the careers and accomplishments of Law School faculty and alumni.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series and two additions: I. Correspondence, 1939-2004, undated. II. Topical Files, 1939-2006, undated.
African Americans -- Civil rights; African Americans -- Legal status, laws, etc.; Compensation (Law) -- United States; Law teachers; Reparations for historical injustices; Restitution -- United States; United States -- Claims; Educators; Lawyers; Bittker, Boris I., 1916-2005; Yale Law School; Yale University -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1939-2004, undated; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  There are two sets of correspondence. The first set is a series of folders arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent.
  The second set is a copy of numbered correspondence from 1980 to 1997 maintained in chronological order. At the beginning of each folder, there is a handwritten index indicating the name of each correspondent and the page number(s) for copies of letters to that individual. For example, the handwritten list for June 1980 to February 1981 indicates that letters to "Adams" will be found on pages 139, 155, and 195. There is no index for the period between July 1996 and November 1997.
  Items outside the specified dates may appear in the folders. Researchers should check each folder for complete accuracy.
  - Abrahamson-Albertus Magnus College, 1968-2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Albrecht-American Bar Foundation, 1966-2001 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Civil Liberties Union-American College of Tax Counsel, 1955-2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Heart Association-Ayres, 1983-2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Aaron, Henry, 1969-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Law Institute, 1961-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Association of University Professors (AAUP)-Arkansas Act 10 Litigation Fund (AALS), 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Arent, Albert E., 1946-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Asimow, Michael R., 1975-1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bachman-Beghe, 1959-2002 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Begleiter-Bhatia, 1969-2004 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Biale-Blumstein, 1949-1998 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Bobbit-Boyle, 1969-2002 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Braden-Brooks, 1961-2004 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Brown-Bywaters, 1958-2004 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Blum, Walter, 1950-1986 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Cabranes-Capron, 1963-2004 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Cardozo-Chambers, 1975-2003 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Chansue-Cochran, 1969-2000 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Coe-Connecticut, 1971-2001 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Conyers-Cutler, 1982-2001 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Case for Black Reparations(Toni Morrison), 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Chirelstein, Marvin, 1955-2004 (Box 4, Folder 23-24)
  - Cleveland State University, 1983-1987 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Coker, Francis W. Jr. and Kathie, 1954-1971 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Commentary, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Cone, Sidney, 1961-1983 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Commission on College Retirement, 1984-1988 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Cooley Lectures (University of Michigan), 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Countryman, Vernon, 1959-2000 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Constitutional Commentary, 1990-1997 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Dahl-Ditkof, 1967-2003 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Diversity-Dworsky, 1960-1999 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Denning, Brannon, 1997-2003 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Easterbrook-Euro-Dutch, 1972-2003 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Emden, Norman and Helen, 1948-1979 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Emerson, Thomas I. and Ruth, 1976-1991 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Emory, Meade, 1977-1995 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Eustice, James, 1964-2002 (Box 5, Folder 40-42)
  - Fair-Firestone, 1972-2002 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - First-Frost, 1969-2004 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Frank, Jerome, 1941-1946 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Frank, Estate of Jerome, 1947-1997 (Box 6, Folder 46-47)
  - Gaggini-George, 1975-1998 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Getman-Gnaizda, 1962-2001 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Gold-Gwynne, 1946-2000 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Ghana taxation, 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Griswold, Erwin N., 1951-1994 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Haber-Hector, 1956-1999 (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - Heider-Hutton, 1960-2000 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - Hamilton, Walton, 1939-1989 (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Hawaii Tax Institute, 1983-1984 (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Idleman-Isenbergh, 1944-2004 (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - Internal Revenue Service
    - General, 1957-1994 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Commissioner v. Clay B. Brown (Clay Brown), 1965 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Jachino-Joseph, 1957-2002 (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - Kabaservice-Kezarian, 1981-2001 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - Killingsworth-Kornhauser, 1976-2002 (Box 8, Folder 62)
  - Kowitz-Kurz, 1899-2004 (Box 8, Folder 63)
  - Kahn, Estate of Joan, 1981-1996 (Box 8, Folder 64)
  - Klein, William A., 1975-1990 (Box 8, Folder 65)
  - Labaton-Laurents, 1968-2000 (Box 8, Folder 66)
  - Lawrence-Lewis, 1981-2003 (Box 8, Folder 67)
  - Lieberman-Lytton, 1980-2004 (Box 8, Folder 68)
  - Little, Brown and Company, 1983-1996 (Box 8, Folder 69)
  - Lokken, Lawrence, 1981-2001 (Box 8, Folder 70)
  - Lyon, Charles S., 1952-1983 (Box 9, Folder 71-73)
  - Macey-Miller, 1952-2003 (Box 9, Folder 74)
  - Mills-Musgrave, 1975-1999 (Box 9, Folder 75)
  - McAniff-McClure, 1968-2000 (Box 9, Folder 76)
  - McMahon-McNulty, 1983-2001 (Box 9, Folder 77)
  - MacDonald, William, 1966-1994 (Box 9, Folder 78)
  - Mueller, Addison, 1951-1981 (Box 10, Folder 79)
  - Nacev-Newman, 1973-2002 (Box 10, Folder 80)
  - New Mexico-Norton, 1965-1997 (Box 10, Folder 81)
  - National Resources Defense Council, 1980-2003 (Box 10, Folder 82-83)
  - New Haven Legal Assistance, Inc., 1982-2003 (Box 10, Folder 84-85)
  - Oakes-Oxford, 1972-2001 (Box 10, Folder 86)
  - Ohio State Law Forum (Black Reparations), 1969-1972 (Box 10, Folder 87)
  - Pacheco-Peat, 1956-2002 (Box 11, Folder 88)
  - Pechman-Pushaw, 1977-2003 (Box 11, Folder 89)
  - Pollack, Louis, 1949-2000 (Box 11, Folder 90)
  - Quigley-Quinnipiac, 1990-1995 (Box 11, Folder 91)
  - Rahdert-Ritter, 1976-2002 (Box 11, Folder 92)
  - Roberts-Rose, 1946-2002 (Box 11, Folder 93)
  - Rosen-Ruttenerg, 1967-2004 (Box 11, Folder 94)
  - Redlich, Norman, 1951-2002 (Box 11, Folder 95)
  - Rostow, Eugene, 1940-2003 (Box 12, Folder 96-97)
  - Rothman & Co., Fred B. (Collected Legal Essays), 1989-1990 (Box 12, Folder 98)
  - Safire-Schlesinger, 1975-2002 (Box 12, Folder 99)
  - Schmidt-Segall, 1970-2002 (Box 12, Folder 100)
  - Serling-Shulter, 1941-2001 (Box 12, Folder 101)
  - Siegan-Stapleton, 1968-2004 (Box 12, Folder 102)
  - Starcher-Swords, 1946-2001 (Box 12, Folder 103)
  - Stern, Carl, 1949-2004 (Box 13, Folder 104-106)
  - Stix family, 1997-1999 (Box 13, Folder 107)
  - Stone, Laurence, 1968-1995 (Box 13, Folder 108)
  - Streng, William, 1977-1987 (Box 13, Folder 109)
  - Taft-Thompson, 1968-1999 (Box 13, Folder 110)
  - Thorne-Tversky, 1972-2000 (Box 13, Folder 111)
  - Treasury Department, 1954-1977 (Box 13, Folder 112)
  - Troyer, Thomas, 1967-1986 (Box 13, Folder 113)
  - Ture, Norman, 1952-1991 (Box 14, Folder 114)
  - Uelmen-Untermyer, 1975-1992 (Box 14, Folder 115)
  - Vafai-Vorenberg, 1976-1994 (Box 14, Folder 116)
  - Wadsworth-Waters, 1978-2001 (Box 14, Folder 117)
  - Watt-Winter, 1971-2001 (Box 14, Folder 118)
  - Wisconsin-Wyzanski, 1965-2001 (Box 14, Folder 119)
  - Wallace, Gerald, 1952-1990 (Box 14, Folder 120)
  - Warren, Alvin, 1975-1987 (Box 14, Folder 121)
  - Warren, Gorham & Lamont, 1991-1995 (Box 14, Folder 122)
  - Weinfeld, Edward, 1952-1986 (Box 14, Folder 122)
  - Yale-Young, 1979-2001 (Box 14, Folder 124)
  - Yale Law Journal, 1970-1999 (Box 14, Folder 125)
  - Yale Law School Class of 1941 Reunion Committee, 1990-2001 (Box 15, Folder 126)
  - Zalenck-Zolt, 1954-2001 (Box 15, Folder 127)
  - June 1980-February 1981, 1980-1981 (Box 15, Folder 128-129)
  - June 1981-January 1982, 1981-1982 (Box 15, Folder 130-131)
  - February 1982-August 1982 (Box 15, Folder 132-133)
  - September 1982-June 1983, 1982-1983 (Box 15, Folder 134-135)
  - July 1983-March 1984, 1983-1984 (Box 15, Folder 136-137)
  - April 1984-June 1985, 1984-1985 (Box 16, Folder 138-140)
  - July 1985-June 1986, 1985-1986 (Box 16, Folder 141-143)
  - July 1986-May 1987, 1986-1987 (Box 16, Folder 144-145)
  - June 1987-May 1988, 1987-1988 (Box 16, Folder 146-147)
  - June 1988-May 1989, 1988-1989 (Box 16, Folder 148-149)
  - June 1989-June 1990, 1989-1990 (Box 17, Folder 150-151)
  - July 1990-June 1991, 1990-1991 (Box 17, Folder 152-153)
  - July 1991-June 1992, 1991-1992 (Box 17, Folder 154-155)
  - September 1992-August 1993, 1992-1993 (Box 17, Folder 156)
  - September 1993-June 30, 1994, 1993-1994 (Box 17, Folder 157)
  - July 1994-June 1996, 1994-1996 (Box 17, Folder 158-160)
  - July 1996-November 1997, 1996-1997 (Box 17, Folder 161-162)
- Topical files, 1939-2006, undated; Series II
  This series includes correspondence, memorandums, newspaper clippings, publications, and other written materials from professional organizations that Boris I. Bittker was employed by, or subject files that he created. Arranged alphabetically by topic or organization name.
  Bittker's participation in the prosecution of German saboteurs during World War II is documented in the folders titled Ex Parte Quirin and Office of Lend-Lease Administration. Bittker's interest in race relations and civil rights are shown in his mid-1960s research on black reparations and his 'Black Lawyer' seminar at Yale Law School.
  - Bittker, Boris I.
    - Bar admissions, 1942-2002 (Box 18, Folder 163)
    - Lectures, 1995 (Box 18, Folder 164)
    - Personal, 1939-2003 (Box 18, Folder 165-166)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 18, Folder 167)
  - Black reparations, 1969-2003 (Box 18, Folder 168-170)
  - Ex Parte Quirin-German saboteurs case, 1942-1997 (Box 18, Folder 171-172)
  - unspecified (Box 19, Folder 173-174)
  - Humor and parody, 1973-1977, 2005-2006 (Box 19, Folder 175)
  - Income Tax-Citizen's Guide, 1975 (Box 19, Folder 176)
  - Istanbul, 2000 (Box 19, Folder 177)
  - Multicultural society, 1990-1991 (Box 19, Folder 178)
  - Office of Lend-Lease Administration (1942-1943), 1942-1945 (Box 19, Folder 179-182)
  - U. S. Treasury Department
    - Clay Brown legislation, 1966 (Box 20, Folder 183)
    - Exempt organization advertising, 1963-1968 (Box 20, Folder 184-186)
  - U. S. v. Jackson, et. al. (Smith Act case), 1957-1958 (Box 20, Folder 187)
  - Yale Law School
    - Publications
      - Legal Affairs magazine, 2002 (Box 20, Folder 188)
      - The Yale Survey of Current Legal Issues, 1995-1996 (Box 20, Folder 189-190)
    - Seminars
      - Black lawyer, 1966-1969 (Box 20, Folder 191)
      - Political and civil rights, 1968-1969 (Box 20, Folder 192)
- Additional material, 1941-1995; Accession 2014-M-011; 0.5; (1 box)
  This accession consists of correspondence, notes, and drafts of several unpublished manuscripts by Bittker.
  - Correspondence, 1941-1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notes, Circa 1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript drafts
    - "A Functional Approach to Future Interests", Circa 1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Future Interests Restated: Tradition versus Clarification and Reform", Circa 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Legal and Equitable Future Interests: a Comparison", 1941
      - Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Typescript (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "The Transmission of Wealth from Generation to Generation...", Circa 1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Unidentified manuscript fragments, Circa 1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Additional material, 1938-1941; Accession 2014-M-060; 0.5; (1 box)
  Handwritten course notes of law courses taken by Bittker, with some Law School examinations (associated with the notes), and "canned briefs" of notes sold by law students.
  - Course notes, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 1-13)